this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at SC - radio dotnet SC radio is
brought to you by the I Triple E
Computer Society I Triple E software
magazine online at computer org slash
software dr. Maria girl Ottawa is an
associate research scholar at Princeton
University Department of Electrical
Engineering and an associate director of
the Princeton edge lab dr. garlotte OVA
earned her PhD in electrical engineering
from Columbia University and her
master's and bachelor's degrees in
electrical engineering from University
of Ottawa Canada she has several years
of industry experience where she had
been affiliated with telcordia
technologies IBM and de sha research dr.
go--let OVA is a recipient of the Google
Anita Borg USA fellowship Canadian
graduate scholar fellowships and the
Columbia University presidential
fellowship she's a co recipient of the
ACM census best student demonstration
award the I Triple E communications
society young author best paper award
and the I Triple E communications
society award for advances in
communications maria garlotte OVA
welcome to the show hiya Diana hi today
we're gonna be talking about edge
computing and also IOT so I want to
begin first with IOT we did an episode
episode 312 about the Internet of Things
but for those that didn't hear that
episode can you give a quick overview of
what IOT is yeah definitely so IOT the
Internet of Things has been set to be
the next big thing for quite some time
so this is the idea of connecting
everyday objects around us imagine if
everything that that you own and
everything and your household could
communicate and network and hats
intelligence built into it so your
spaces would be smart your your factory
is smart cities that all forms the part
of this vision of a fully connected
world and the driver there are lots of
very interesting technical challenges
towards making this happen so how do you
actually connect a lot all of those
billions of nodes how you do it in an
energy efficient way so that you can
connect mobile devices how you would do
it the right way in terms of preserving
security and privacy of the different
users so there are tremendous
opportunities and it's a very
interesting field but there are lots of
technical challenges to be solved mm-hmm
you mentioned nodes and energy
efficiencies and I know IOT at this
point is everywhere can you give some
examples of where IOT is like what kind
of device and what is it doing yeah
definitely so you can think of all the
fitness trackers for example as IO two
objects so these are small so for things
like Fitbit for example that you put on
your hand and that track your your
activities now that's what that's one
example that and this gives you a
different level of understanding of your
behavior then you could get with manual
recording for example other smart toys a
smart factory is all the different
connected equipment there that's all
Internet of Things mm-hmm and as I
mentioned earlier the main focus of this
show is gonna be at computing which is
very related to IOT the Internet of
Things
can you explain what it's computing is
yeah definitely so each computing is the
idea of bringing in intelligence from
from the cloud to devices that are
around you so for example to smart
computing gateways or to computers that
are specifically installed close to the
users for advanced processing and
advanced data storage currently a lot of
functionality for even for things like
smart assistants for example
all of the data that is collected is
actually sent to the cloud for
processing for all the different IOT
nodes that is the case and that that has
some limitations so each computing is
about taking some functionality closer
to the users while keeping some other
advanced computing functionality on the
cloud and having endpoint devices and
the cloud work together to do data
processing and responsiveness and
storage and control in the best possible
way taking advantage of the latency and
data locality close to the users while
taking advantage of this massive
computing power that that the cloud has
so what you mentioned is bringing some
of the intelligence from the cloud to
the smart devices we talked about feed
bit earlier so in a sense it would be
enable that Fitbit to do some computing
in the feed bit right just to imagine
this so if you talked about Fitbit for
example that would be a more having your
smartphone do additional processing for
for your Fitbit rather than sending out
lots of data to the cloud have some of
the processing advanced processing be
done on a smartphone or on a local
gateway yes but that's true because now
the Fitbit connects to the phone but if
the Fitbit itself was just on its own I
guess it would yeah yeah so you could
basically in the internet of things
these days their architecture more or
less standardizes own having those types
of gateways that can help your end
devices so typical internet-of-things
architecture these days is what's called
three-tier architecture low end nodes
gateways that are plugged in or that are
otherwise more capable and then the
cloud so in this case your smartphone is
the is the 8 edge device in terms are in
a smart home type of architecture where
you have for example connected
lightbulbs and connected connected
doorbells and connected fridges and all
all of that there are a smart gateways
that can be made more intelligent so for
example Samsung smart gateways and all
others mm-hmm
for existing devices what is some of
that cloud functionality that can be
moved to them
currently basically a pretty much every
responsive functionality that is fairly
advanced it's all processed on the cloud
so any type of learning that happens
that all happens on the cloud even the
responses that you get from for example
from the likes of Alexa for all the
different elements of recognition that
is all done on the cloud and you can
really move some of this much closer to
enable more more responsiveness another
element that that is very interesting
about edge computing is that if you do
some of the processing locally that is
currently done on the cloud you can do
better in terms of privacy so while in
some cases your performance may not
necessarily be better than called
performance you alleviate a lot of
concerns if you keep your raw data
streams local if no cloud entity
receives full access to your raw data I
see and what would be some things that
would be hard to move to the devices
right now just because the devices
themselves could have been made not for
this in particular so they don't have
the hardware capabilities yeah that's a
great question so device local devices
will always be less capable than the
cloud in the cloud you talk about huge
server planes the opportunity to use
multiple cores for the different
processing you talk about massive
storage so while you can deploy a local
servers that could theoretically come
closer to the capabilities it's not
realistic so your gateways and your
small devices will always be limited and
so there there will always be elements
of processing that should
they own the cloud and this is for
example processing of massive datasets
global datasets global data global state
that is collected from hundreds and
thousands of users you wouldn't want to
move that type of processing to the
local device you can keep processing
that is relevant to you local but it's
not that you would ever load other users
data to your local conditions long also
other things that that really should
stay on the cloud is items related to
long term processing and storage for
example that in the cloud as a backup
that it's very natural for for that to
be on the cloud cloud as as a way of
keeping essentially global states we
we've been playing around with the idea
of let's say that we have a network of
drones where we have what Amazon is
imagining about drone based package
delivery so in this scenario your global
state of all the drones around the
country for example that would be global
the information about drones that are in
a particular area that can be handled by
a regional H server for example and then
the information about the very very
local drones that are particular to your
specific building for example or a
specific small neighborhood that can be
held only a very local node so this is
the kind of hierarchical separation that
is imagined with agent for computing I
see
and part of this motivation is it
because of the that notion of data
locality in latency benefits yeah that's
exactly right yes so we there are
inherent limits to latency as your
signals have to travel farther and
farther away so there are bounds that
just cannot be crossed and you will
always be a faster but local nodes just
from from the physics of it
the data locality element is is the
other one that you you will always
essentially save costs you will save
network you will always benefit in one
way or another if you manage to keep
your data local I see yes also because
of this importance of privacy in this
space right that's exactly right yeah
that's that's exactly that's exactly
that part of your work involves
evaluating edge computing and for this I
saw that you created an edge computing
testbed
can you explain what this is yes so
we've created a fairly small setup that
allows us to test some of the ideas
around doing local processing and remote
processing jointly for fairly
complicated operations that are
currently done on the cloud so we've
picked an example of machine learning
specifically we picked a regression but
it doesn't have to be a regression any
type of a machine learning raishin could
could be done there and we've
implemented some ideas around data
locality that we do part of the machine
learning training locally without moving
the data to the cloud and then some
devices move some of the raw data to the
cloud and then the partial local models
get combined in a way that is in machine
learning they called ensemble learning
so a combination of locally obtained
models and this is in contrast to what
is currently done for training systems
where all of the data from all the
devices gets moved to one location and
machine learning algorithm iterates over
it in one place so so we've built a
testbed that allows us to play with
these ideas we have local nodes we use
raspberry PI's for both data collection
and for local processing for this local
model computation and on the cloud side
currently we are using an AWS back-end
lambda
and DynamoDB for processing on that site
we collect basic information we
essentially instrument that our
raspberry pies but sans have boards that
collect different types of sensor
information around that they are
observing temperature pressure some
other parameters so some of the
raspberry PI's are sensor nodes that
simply collect this information while
others do this kind of local computing
and weave instrument and the testbed to
measure all the different parameters
that are important to an edge computing
system the latency of the overall
processing the quality of the results of
the learning that we achieve and also
we've implemented to measure costs and
we use just actual costs that Amazon is
charging us for for the processing on
lambda but we can also plug in a
different back-end and try other things
in terms of costs so it's it's a it's a
system where you can really play with
this distributed learning ideas
essentially mm-hmm so in this case the
edge computing nodes are the raspberry
PI's that's right yes and you're saying
these are connected this communicate to
AWS yes yep that's right yes several of
them communicate through AWS and we use
serverless processing on the W side and
you mentioned in this case this test but
the focus was a linear regression
experiment so itself the notes what are
they doing the raspberry PI's yes so
they are
do they are calculating essentially
regression models vocally and some of it
some of them calculate regression models
locally and some of them send their raw
information to the cloud and those
partial models and the raw data get
combined to create one global model and
you also mention AWS lambda for those
that aren't
can you explain what that consists of oh
yes so cloud processing comes in
different flavors for a while the cloud
computing architectures have
standardized on essentially providing
capabilities that are in ways similar to
what you would have locally a virtual
machine that you can use like you would
be using your local computer relatively
recently starting from about 2013 what
what's called serverless architectures
have started to be explored there it's
not that you rent a machine from iws or
a core or rather there is a specific
function that you write that aw swell
run for you so you do not have to create
a server instance you do not have to
reserve a virtual machine there is a
function that will get instantiate that
on demand and well BM will be performing
the action that you'd like so in AWS the
server's functionality is called lambda
other cloud providers offered as well
under different names but it's a very
interesting idea that is kind of a
win-win from the point of view of both
end users and call providers the likes
of a double years essentially use their
spare capacities to provide this type of
on-demand functionality so this allows
them to use the types of resources that
are traditionally underused for them on
the user side using lambda and other
server less functions allows you to in
some cases process your information much
cheaper as you only pay for the server
time that that you use you also don't
have to worry about having your virtual
machine up and running that has
advantages there as well but the
downside is that there are some limits
that come with that the there is a
startup time
there are some restrictions as to how
you can write your functionality but
overall what's very interesting about
lambda and other server list
functionality is that it has been
specifically recommended for a lot of
IOT solutions for a lot of internet of
things jobs as they have this type of a
property that once data comes in it
needs to be processed but you do not
necessarily need to run your virtual
machine at all at all times so this is
where where that comes in a long answer
to a simple question yeah that's a great
answer for the example we were talking
about where we have the raspberry PI's
running linear regression models and
then they communicate through way WS
lambda or they send information to AWS
lambda what is the function in this case
what is the function in charge of the
function is in charge of combining the
partial models so combining the partial
models and coming up with a global model
that represents the summary of the
learning of the local devices I see and
in this particular experiment I'm
curious in what ways those linear
regression need to be adapted for it
computing what was the motivation of
choosing this yes so so in there are
several benefits in this case and also
in key in other cases where you can do
local learning one of the benefits is
usually you use less bandwidth you tax
the network less as you go from always
sending all of your raw bit streams to
sending only partial or it's essentially
from to only sending features for the
nodes that did processing locally so you
can see it important savings in network
utilization and important savings in
cloud computing costs that are
associated with it so
element is just this is a better use of
network resources another benefit is a
data privacy that you do not send raw
data to the cloud from all nodes it has
only some nodes that do that and overall
your you are achieving these savings and
benefits at fairly reasonable trade-offs
in terms of the quality of the results
so you are gaining you you are reducing
costs and you're gaining privacy at very
reasonable reductions in quality of
learning basically some of these
raspberry PI's are acting as sensors in
that the environment they're at can you
talk about data sensing and collection
and analytics that the local IOT devices
are doing yeah we used the the boards
that are called the cells have boards
they have several different sensors that
collect environmental information
temperature pressure a couple of other
things so we use those raspberry pi is
equipped with a sense hats as
essentially emulators of other types of
IOT nodes you can think of them as
emulators of fitbit like functionality
or connected lightbulbs and what is the
linear regression machine learning
trying to learn we will be looking at
correlations of the different
environmental parameters essentially so
we are trying to predict one
environmental parameter from a number of
others but they really you'll be using
here linear regression specifically in
these sensors as well as just emulators
of any other types of learning or
environmental data collection that that
you would be doing when I was reading
about this experiment I saw that a
subset of these IOT devices are acting
as computing gateways are these
ones that are doing the linear
regression computations yeah that's
right yes so the assumption is that so
for example in a smart home if you have
your Samsung Gateway and you have small
endpoint sensors the smart gateway would
be the one that does local learning
local processing I see and as part of
some of the bottlenecks that edge
computing resolves in existing machine
learning can you talk a little bit more
about those for learning specifically
that the two big questions that this
type of an approach addresses is privacy
and network utilization so you can
imagine that if you do not transmit as
much raw data to the cloud you keep your
network free to do other things which
helps you essentially spend your network
resources on providing more immediate
services and more on I own other things
so you lower the utilization of networks
for these learning problems and the
other big issue that this approach
addresses is privacy not transmitting
private data to the cloud this is
however only one use case for for each
computing a local training does not have
this element of benefitting latency that
other approaches to each computing have
so this is one of the one of the ways of
using edge computing from your
experience what have been the main
technical challenges needed to enable
edge that is a great questions there are
many different ones and they come in
different flavors and different
researchers consider different types of
problems I am very interested in this
question of adapting computing for edge
systems
traditionally the the types of work
types of work that look at for example
distributing computing for different
elements of data locality they do not
consider this element of local node
being less capable for example than the
global node you're all games that have
been designed for centralized operation
and al games that have been designed for
running in multiple cores of a server
that where different cores have roughly
same capabilities all of those al games
have to be adapted for this type of each
computing settings and that updations
are non non-trivial not straightforward
so they require research they require
digging into the mechanics of fairly
complex iterative algorithms so that
that's that's one big challenge that a
lot of work needs to be done that is on
the algorithmic level for this there are
there are not also a lot of challenges
on the software level in the sense that
we are we are used to having even with
serverless computing for example we are
used to having the cloud instantiate
different things for us on demand but
how to achieve these in local devices it
either there are interesting challenges
there and important problems to be
solved which specific functionality you
should you have on any specific local
node how to make sure that that is
available for the users how to make sure
that the handoff is handled right we
between different local nodes all of
fairly traditional questions in resource
instantiation they all have important
considerations that need to be solved
for H specifically for the first one
that you mentioned about adapting
computing for edge systems are these
mostly driven by the hardware
limitations of the edge nodes yes
hardware limitations on one side
desire to say save energy
also the element of possible interrupted
connectivity between the local devices
and the cloud those all come into play
can you talk a little bit more about the
approach to start coming up with an
adaptation do you begin by looking at
the hardware or the algorithm itself
just a quick overview of what that
process looks like oh that very that is
an interesting question I think where
people come up with this is I think that
depends on one's background you can
start by looking at the assumptions that
are made in the existing all games and
seeing what needs to be adapted for
limited resources on the edge you can
also look at this concept of what I need
to do if I want to keep my data local
let's say that we have algorithms that
demand the data to be in one place you
can start thinking about what how you
would need to change them if you wanted
to not move the data those are a couple
of directions that you could take I want
to talk now a little bit more about the
architecture for edge computing when I
was researching for this I saw one term
that is uses that the architecture is
horizontal
can you explain what this means so
basically there are horizontal here in
this column in this context means a
solution that serves multiple different
verticals so a solution that is not
specifically tailored to for example
smart factories but a solution much like
the current called computing systems
that different users can adapt to the
different needs another area that I've
seen you explore in terms of
architecture is this notion of the
fundamental pillars of the edge
one of them is security and scalability
can you explain this a little bit more
yes so security is of course a huge
concern in the internet of things it is
arguably one of the reasons why one of
the limiters to the deployment of the
Internet of Things so security is is of
course a huge concern as you have the
devices that are very close to you that
have your data that interact with you
very personally that I interact with
your household very personally so
security and privacy in the Internet of
Things is a concern always and one of
the pillars emphasizes that in terms of
each computing there is a difference
there is an added element to that in
that in terms of security one of the
benefits of a data center architecture
is that all the different computing
nodes are essentially under lock and key
they're all in one place and you have
physical security of those different
computing nodes but each computing a
couple of assumptions change your
processing node your computing node is
no longer physically secure so you you
can have a user alter what happens in it
and affect the processing in ways that
you would not have in the data center so
there is an elevated security risk from
that point of view on the other hand if
you manage to secure local devices then
you can do better in terms of providing
privacy for the users as it if you keep
the your very sensitive very local data
to your local node that feels much
better than sending it to the cloud but
you do need to make sure that security
is addressed for these types of local
conditions so this is where security
comes in to play as a very important
element of IOT and H computing systems
specifically in terms of scalability
this is a constant concern that is
common to all distributed system
architectures that you need
to make sure that the solutions you
design are able to support thousands
millions and billions of nodes and
whatever solutions that you come up with
I need to need to scale going back to
security like you said one of this is
because of the notion of the data by
this what I'm imagining because it's
what I talked about in the IOT episode
and I've seen it on the news is these
teddy bears or toys that are just inside
a house and yes yeah so so the main
security concern there is also what data
is this bear gathering is that correct
so researchers tend to distinguish
between security and privacy while
sometimes those are combined together
alright so in terms of the data that is
gathered that typically goes under
that's typically referred to as privacy
security concerns would be more along
the lines of inserting viruses into the
system or corrupting corrupting other
users data using the information that
you gather locally or hurting oh my god
I don't want to save but using the teddy
bear not just to collect the information
but to hurt people around it I see what
you're saying they get control of the
teddy bear and then the teddy bear can
do something else I see for example that
a teddy bear I think is imagined more is
a passive device but so for example if
you have your local video cameras that
are controlled via internet you could
theoretically disconnect the camera or
carpel it if you want to break into a
house so that that starts to go into
these personal personal security and not
only cyber security but also personal
security elements the other part that
you mentioned under security was that
the device is not physically secure
it was not very clear to me if by this
you mean like somebody can grab that
teddy bear just open it and the data is
there in the teddy bear is that what you
meant in the world of of security one of
the core premises of it is that if you
have device in your physical possession
you can you have access to pretty much
everything so you can do everything but
the device if you have it physically so
in in your traditional cloud computing
systems your multiple users are sharing
a server for example but none of them
have that server physically so all of
that the physical security of the server
is handled by the third party who we all
trust and that is that is under lock and
key in each computing systems your your
processing device is local so if you
want to use that device for processing
elements of other users data or if you
want to use that local device for any
types of processing that interacts with
the cloud you have to pay additional
attention to how you secure those
interactions as you may assume that a
malicious user could compromise this
node and do damage to the node as well
as to their other computing functions if
the user can access them just by having
physical control of the node in terms of
scalability what are the current
challenges that are being explored by
people working on edge computing so I
don't necessarily want to answer this
one as this isn't my specialty and your
specialty or one of your main focuses is
this part of adapting the computing for
the edge right yep yeah pretty much here
yeah adapting computing the different
responsive elements as well as training
types of elements yeah I see one of the
other pillars of the edge is open
can you explain what this means so in
this work we are imagining having an
architecture where all of the different
components are available to two other
people so the idea of in open structure
as opposed to a proprietary solution
that has a black box elements that
others cannot work with how is this
similar to autonomy which is the other
pillar of the edge autonomy is a very
interesting question for each systems
autonomy implies ability to make
decisions without the cloud currently
things like smart assistants for example
they really do need the cloud to operate
in meaningful ways in many cases
autonomy is the element that allows us
to actual decision-making and
responsiveness locally without having
cloud as a constant back-end so this
requires some elements of computing
restructuring that are non-trivial what
are some examples of decisions that
could be made by the edge the types of
inference that are currently running on
on the cloud computing systems so for
example image recognition voice
recognition all of these all of these
types of things you can do that locally
there are ways of adapting models to
restricted local conditions there are
elements of suggestions as what is
currently fully tree fully completely
all nearly always done on the cloud so
for example suggestions of the next
soundtrack for you to listen to that can
be done locally if there is very
interesting work that talks about this
in person
personalizing those experiences as
opposed to having them done on the cloud
and it really is becoming very very
powerful these days the things that you
can do about local devices any types of
support that you would need for video
processing
identifying if there are important
objects in the video identifying if the
video changes in important ways between
different elements all of that can be
done locally a support for support for
drones supports for autonomous cars
there's a lot of functionality there
that can be fully moved to the edge and
the main component for this you said is
personalization of experiences and it's
one of the components yes you can value
personalization could be one of the
values the other values are the slightly
reduced latency and improved quality
because of the richness of local
information the other pillar that I want
to talk about is ideally can you give an
example of what this means currently the
way that cloud computing is this is this
is a very good question this is a very
interesting element of each computing
currently a lot of the work that is done
with the cloud it has this flavor of
collecting vast quantities of data
processing it say overnight and coming
up with an update that is this once in a
while so you're computing systems
updates your learning updates all happen
on these very good external long
timescales agility means that we can go
from collecting data to making a
decision on that data to acting on that
data at a much different scale so rather
than waiting for these and weeks and
months to collect the data and process
it we can get to the point where we are
we're collecting data we are
incorporating it into our existing
knowledge and we are acting on it in the
loop very quickly so this is a different
time scale of operations and a very
different level of experience than what
we currently have with the existing
systems in a sense agility is leveraging
the autonomy pillar because it's like
you said it's going from collecting the
data because devices can have sensors
and then making the decision itself
right the
that's exactly right here that's that's
a that's a great way of putting it
the last pillar that I want to talk
about is hierarchy what for example what
does the edge deployment look like yes
one thing to note about a lot of
existing distributed systems
architectures is that they are flat so
your cloud platforms are flat they are a
collection of essentially equal service
servers for the equal cores and a
traditional peer-to-peer systems like
Napster for example back in the days
they also fled their collection of
appears that are equal in capabilities
with edge systems you have different
levels of nodes that are very different
in capabilities you have the cloud that
is massive that is far away that has a
lot of computing process computing
capabilities lots of storage but but
it's far you have regional nodes that
are very powerful as well they're a
little closer they are smaller than your
cloud nodes they may offer different
trade-offs in terms of latency in terms
of quality of processing you go down and
down that hierarchy level until you get
to local gateways that could be mobile
like your phone that could be very much
reduced in their processing capabilities
that could have fractions of the cores
of cloud nodes and then you get down to
the endpoint devices that are trying to
save energy that have very restricted
CPUs that may I may want to sleep for
long periods of time to save their
energy this is the the hierarchical
structure is essential to to these
systems it's there and you really need
to figure out solutions that take
advantage of what those different layers
have to offer you so you really need to
be designing solutions that are
hierarchically in this way and it's it
is a bit silly that it is non-trivial
to do that but just traditionally
computer computer systems
have not been designed like this so
there are a lot of very interesting
challenges in figuring out how to take
advantage of this type of hierarchy and
heterogeneity of the different nodes in
the hierarchy one example that I saw in
in a talk that you gave regarding these
pillars of the edge and particularly
hierarchy is the smart city example can
you describe the smart city yes so smart
cities are a great applica great example
of this vision for going from a data
center based computing to computing
around you in a traditional system right
now we have all the nodes in a smart
city they collect their data from from
their sensors and they send it to a
cloud data center that can be hundreds
or thousands of miles away so the
signals travel there in the HKH
computing for computing smart city we
will have nodes that are processing the
data much closer to the users so you
would have a computing node in your
house you would have a computing node in
your building on your street corner in
the zip code in the neighborhood a
regional node and the global cloud node
and all those different nodes can be
responsible for different parts of
processing and working together I get
the right types of latency is the light
right types of reliabilities and the
more interactive more advanced
experience that you need in a smart city
with smart transportation in the
adaptive behavior that that requires one
thing you just described is you can have
a computing node in your house and then
in this hierarchy next comes the
regional node what would be an example
of something that original node can be
in charge of so I think the hierarchies
could have multiple levels between the
house and the regional node currently
for example companies like Comcast they
already have a box in your household and
they already have elements of
architecture that are not so much
regional as neighborhood based so you
and that's one of the elements that that
could be envisioned your your notes that
are the next level from your household
notes notes that are responsible for
different areas like a region or a zip
code or a neighborhood they could be
responsible for decision making and
analytics and tracking that is
responsible that is specific to that
region so for example data collection
that aggregates that tastes of the
different household in the households
and you zip code the information about
channel conditions and local mappings
that is particular to a specific area
that the node is responsible for
information about the the upcoming
specific specific upcoming changes to
that specific neighborhood for example
if you have a stadium in your in your
region in your neighborhood and the
stadium is expected to have a game then
there could be certain adaptations to
communications and to other parameters
that the node could be responsible for
making so this is really this level of
hierarchical responsibilities if you
would or also for electricity
electricity communications computing all
of those come into play yes mapping for
smart for smart infrastructures what do
you mean about mapping so currently for
for things like drones augmented and
virtual reality and autonomous driving
the idea of knowing exactly local
features of the environment that that's
very important so for one way that you
can imagine using local nodes is to
collect all those different types of
mappings at a very high fidelity levels
much higher than what
you can get with current global
solutions and the mappings could be
physical mappings or where everything is
or they could be mappings of wireless
channel qualities or other parameters
and then the global one could be just
aggregating all this data from the
regional ones and providing some other
type of analytics right right right so
providing the different levels of
fidelity at different levels using their
capabilities of local nodes to track
local features that may not be important
on the global level but that are
important locally and that help local
nodes make the best decisions one term
that you mentioned when you were
describing the smart city and the
computing notes in a house was you could
have at computing or fog what is the
difference between edge and fog
currently the terminology in the space
of agent for computing hasn't really
been fully standardized and oftentimes
the terms are used interchangeably they
have some distinctions in certain
contexts usually fog relates to the idea
of spanning the range from devices to
the cloud so having all the different
nodes work together at the different
levels of the hierarchy
while each in certain contexts refers to
taking the functionality and moving it
closer to the users I tend to use the
terms interchangeably also when I think
of fog I think more naturally about
different devices working
collaboratively and when I talk about
edge I think more naturally about
creating the best possible local
behavior and there's this consortium
called open fog
can you explain what it is open fog is
one of the organizations that drives
forward this vision of for computing of
the different devices at the different
hierarchies level was working together
open fog was founded in 2016 and
includes a range of organizations from
around the world that want to develop
this type of open hierarchical agile
secure architecture for everyone to use
it has a number of universities a number
of leading companies in hardware space
as well as in computing space and the
goal is to drive forward this vision
essentially why is it important that we
have a consortium like open fog working
in this space it's in the space of
communications and in new architectures
in general you you always running the
risk of everyone going down their own
route and creating solutions that are
incompatible and that do not follow the
same principles in IOT arguably one of
the big issues at this time is
fragmentation that we have so many
protocols and so many alternatives and
so many different approaches that it's
very difficult to move forward with any
one deployment so open fog like other
console era in the space of
communication space of communication and
networking targets creating a unified
view and a unified architecture to help
everyone move forward in the same
direction as otherwise it's very easy to
come up with silent solutions that leave
startups and everybody who develops
products in the VA's uncertainty of
which way should I be following what
what exactly should they be doing so the
goal of the consortium is to get
everyone on the on the same page about
this basically is this also about
establishing standards and guidelines
for example in terms of security and
privacy
alright the end part part of this
establishing a common vision is creating
shared standards so we actually working
on on an I Triple E standard that
describes the open folk architecture I
see
and you mentioned members of this are in
both universe
and company's right yeah so open folk
has over 50 members I believe at this
time all over the world large companies
like Intel Cisco Microsoft a number of
telecom Giants and others as well as a
number of startups and a number of
universities that are taking more of a
research look on formulated elements and
the universities in open fog include
Colorado Boulder
Princeton Arizona State Shanghai Tech
and quite a few others are we still in
the early days of standardizing this
edge computing I believe so yes I
believe we're in the early stages of
this field in general and we are
definitely early in the standardization
space security is one big element that
that needs to be addressed and in
general it's a it's an actively
developing field so I think we are only
scratching the surface on a lot of
questions in it one of the other things
that you wanted to talk about in this
show was the vision for the future of
edge and in particular I'd like to ask
you in terms of your area of focus which
is adapting computing for the edge what
do you see coming next in the in the
next few years so be you so if you
started touching on on some of this I
think I am a huge enthusiast about the
area that is called embedded AI or
intelligence on the edge or essentially
using learning that is currently at
traditionally used on these longer
timescales and on the cloud on local
nodes and the levels of capability is
that you can be reaching there are
absolutely unbelievable so we mentioned
personalization for example currently
machine learning is there there's one
model that is common to everybody and
that responds to your conditions there
are some advances that are showing that
you can have fully local local learning
you can have training that is particular
to you the reinforcement learning you
can achieve fantastic Heights these days
so the the ability of making truly
intelligent decisions truly intelligence
suggestions in at a short timeframe
enabled by fog or edge that that I
believe will be absolutely
transformational we are only at the very
beginning of this very exciting field so
we will have the absolute the next level
of intelligence of a lot of different
experiences does this also have the
potential to be used for example people
that live in places that don't have the
best network resources so sometimes they
get Wi-Fi but could they potentially
just be running this intelligence of
line for example to identify crops and
those kind of models yeah right right so
you you can have the type of behavior
that currently requires the cloud you
you can do locally and or you can do it
with but limited connectivity you you
can have a transition between settings
but good connectivity and poor
connectivity that is seamless that
responds to the different conditions so
that that is it's very exciting and in
that regard yes well Maria thank you so
much for taking the time to come on the
show it's been a pleasure talking to you
about edge computing I think you're
doing a pleasure to talk to you thank
you thanks for listening to se radio an
educational program brought to you by I
Triple E software magazine for more
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website at se - radio
net to provide feedback you can comment
on each episode on the website or reach
us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or
through our slack channel at se
radio.com
you can also email us a team at SC -
radio net this and all other episodes of
SU radio is licensed under Creative
Commons license 2.5 thanks for listening